Guide to the Ireland House Oral History Collection AIA.030
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- S
  - Staunton, Ciarán, 2016; cuid34844 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_66)
    Ciarán Staunton was born in 1963 in County Galway, Ireland and was raised in Louisburgh, County Mayo. He immigrated to the United States in 1982, settling in Boston, Massachusetts and moving to New York, New York in 1991. He owned a number of bars in Boston and New York. He helped for the Irish Immigration Reform Movement in 1987 and co-founded the Irish Lobby for Immigration Reform in 2005. He married and had two children.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll at the Rory Staunton Foundation for Sepsis Prevention in New York, New York on November 10, 2016. The interview covers Ciarán Staunton's early life in Ireland, his working life, and his participation in immigration reform organizations. Staunton discusses his childhood in Ireland and his extended family. He recounts his management of the family's farm and his decision to leave Ireland in 1980. He recounts jobs he held in bars in England, his decision to immigrate to the United States, the benefits of the indefinite validity visa he received. He describes in detail his experiences in Boston, Massachusetts and New York, including his work experiences in Irish bars in Boston and his involvement in Irish immigration and human rights organizations, including Irish Northern Aid Committee (NORAID), Irish Immigration Reform Movement, and Irish Lobby for Immigration Reform. He discusses his involvement with the Friends of Sinn Féin and the peace process in Northern Ireland in the 1990s. Staunton also discusses his son's, Rory, death from sepsis, his establishment of the Rory Staunton Foundation for Sepsis Prevention, and the work of the foundation.
  - Sullivan, John, Apr 20, 2012; cuid34730 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    John Sullivan (b. Manchester, England, 1945) was born in Manchester, England and came to the United States with his family in 1949. He has family roots in Cos. Kerry and Mayo. Before his retirement, he was in charge of marketing and sales for ABB in North America.
  - Sullivan, Maureen, undated; cuid34731 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Maureen Sullivan (b. Brooklyn, New York, 1943), the daughter of immigrants from Counties Clare and Roscommon, was raised in Brooklyn. She spent her early career teaching and working in the advertising industry. She is the President of Maureen Sullivan Communications and the author of two children's books, Ankle Soup and Custard and Mustard.
  - Sweetman, Ruth, May 15, 2013; cuid34732 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    Ruth Sweetman (b. Palmerstown, Co. Dublin, Ireland, 1942) grew up outside of Dublin and has strong family ties to the struggle for Irish independence in the early 20th century. She is the niece of the Irish patriot, Kevin Barry. One of her most treasured possessions is a bracelet which was presented to her mother and is inscribed, "To Eileen M Barry with esteem from St Ita's Committee New York Aug 1929." She was a guidance counselor at the elite bording school, Clongowes Wood.
- T
  - Tahaney, Sr. Anne and Sr. Margaret, Jan 23, 2013, Feb 7, 2012; cuid34733 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    Sr. Anne Tahaney and Sr. Margaret Tahaney (b. Long Island City, New York, 1931; b. New York, New York, 1929) of the Dominican Order are both children of Irish immigrants. They traveled to Pakistan in 1957 and taught at a Dominican school there while also living and working in the local community.
  - Tatty, Matthew, Mar 7, 2009; cuid34734 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Tanner, Peggy, Nov 24, 2008; cuid34735 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PCM660. The interview is approximately 40 minutes long, on 1 CD. The interview took place in Bayville, New Jersey, on November 24, 2008, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
    Peggy Tanner was born in the Bronx in 1929, but moved with her family back to Kilgarvan, Co. Kerry, Ireland, as a young child during the Depression. Her father, Denis Hegarty, was a commandant in the IRA who fought in the 1916 Easter Rising. Peggy trained as a nurse in England in 1947 and immigrated to America in 1953, where she continued her work in nursing. She became involved in local politics in New York and served on the Advisory Committee on Parks and Landscapes.
  - Taylor, Joe, Jan 29, 2009; cuid34736 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Joe Taylor was born in 1937 in Co. Leitrim, Ireland. He settled in New York in the early 1960s and became a member of the Leitrim Association of New York, where he served as president from 1994-1996. His daughter Margaret is also in the organization and was president from 2001-2003. Joe worked as a bartender for thirty years at the Liffey Bar in Queens.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PCM660. The interview is approximately 1 hour long, on 1 CD. The interview took place in Elmhurts, New York, on January 29, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Tierney, Kenneth, undated; cuid34737 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Thomas, Mary, undated; cuid34738 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Tolle, Brian, 2015; cuid34845 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_63)
    Brian Tolle was born in Queens, New York. He received a bachelor's degree in political science from the States University of New York at Albany and a bachelor's degree in fine arts from the Parsons School of Design in Manhattan. He was awarded the commision of the Irish Hunger Memorial in New York City in 2000.
    This interview was conducted by Miriam Nyhan at New York University's Glucksman Ireland House in Manhattan, New York on August 13, 2015. The interview contains Brian Tolle's family history, education, and his design of the Irish Hunger Memorial in New York City between 2000 and 2002. He describes his anxiety of framing the historical events of the past for a contemporary audience. He recounts the way in which he wanted to create an environment where the half acre of land would let viewers interpret their own opinion about the Great Famine in Ireland in the 1840s. He describes his memories of witnessing the terrorist attack on the World Trade Center in New York on September 11th, 2001.
    September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001 -- Personal narratives.
  - Tracey, Patrick, Apr 2, 2012; cuid34739 (Box 4, Folder 88)
    Patrick Tracey (b. Boston, Massachusetts, 1958) is the son of Irish-American parents and can trace his family?s roots to Famine-era Co. Roscommon. He is the author of Stalking Irish Madness: Searching for the Roots of My Family's Schizophrenia.
  - Tubridy, Dan, Dec 2, 2011; cuid34740 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    Dan Tubridy (b. Rockaway, New York, 1948) is the grandchild of Irish immigrants from Counties Kerry and Clare and can trace his family?s Irish lineage back to the eighteenth century. He is the owner of the Bungalow Bar in Far Rockaway, which was featured on Spike TV's Bar Rescue.
  - Tunney, Jay R., Mar 29, 2012; cuid34741 (Box 4, Folder 90)
    Jay R. Tunney (b. New York, New York, 1936) grew up in Stanford, CT, and is the son of Irish-American world heavyweight-boxing champion Gene Tunney. He is the author of The Prizefighter and the Playwright, in which he chronicles his father's relationship with the renowned playwright George Bernard Shaw.
- V
  - Vajrathan-Childers, Monica, undated; cuid34742 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Monica Vajrathan-Childers (b. Bangkok, Thailand, 1936) has ancestry from County Cork. She is the daughter of a Thai mother and a father with Irish and Swiss ancestry. Her grandfather was Joseph Culfield James (1860-1925), principal tutor to the Thai Royal Family. After attending university in Bangkok, Paris, and Illinois she worked for the United Nations in Asia and New York. She married Erskine Childers III, the journalist and son of Irish President Erskine Hamilton Childers (1905-1974). In New York they both held positions at the United Nations and developed relationships with key Irish diplomats and civil servants, including Sean MacBride and Garret Fitzgerald. She has contributed to international dialogue on women's rights and also works as a visual artist.
- W
  - Wall, Eamonn, Nov 30, 2011, Apr 4, 2013; cuid34743 (Box 4, Folder 91)
    Eamonn Wall (b. Enniscorthy, Co. Wexford, Ireland, 1955) emigrated to the United States in 1982 and currently lives in St. Louis, Missouri, where he teaches Irish, Irish-American, and British Literature courses at UM ? St. Louis. He has published six collections of poetry and two books, including Writing the Irish West: Ecologies and Traditions and From the Sin-é Café to the Black Hills.
  - Walsh, James, Sep 27, 2013; cuid34744 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    James P. Walsh (b. San Francisco, California, 1937) is the son of Irish parents from Co. Mayo. He is currently Professor Emeritus of History at San Jose State University and lives in San Francisco, California.
  - Walsh, Peter, 2014; cuid34846 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_12)
    Peter Walsh was born in 1947 in New York, New York. He graduated from Mount St. Michael High School in the Bronx and attended Marist College in Poughkeepsie between 1965 and 1968. He studied at the University of London in London, England in 1969. Walsh served in the United States Army during the Vietnam War. After the war he graduated from Trinity College in Hartford, Connecticut.
    This interview was conducted by Miriam Nyhan on June 30, 2014 at New York University's Glucksman Ireland House in Manhattan, New York. This interview contains Peter Walsh's description of his family's history as immigrants and later as Irish Americans. He recounts stories about his great-grandmother, and his father's childhood stories during the Great Depression. He describes his childhood as an Irish American in New York, his education, and his first trip to Ireland.
  - Waters, Mary, undated; cuid34745 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Mary Waters (b. New York, 1927) is the past president of the Cork Association of New York.
  - Waters, Sr. Victor, Apr 8, 2009; cuid34746 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Sr. Victor Waters was born in Cornamona, Co. Galway, Ireland, in 1904. She immigrated to Chicago in 1925 with her two brothers, one of whom was fleeing the Black and Tans. She entered the order of the Franciscan Sisters in Boston in 1928, and served in Rome for four years during World War II.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 50 minutes long, on 1 CD. The interview took place in Tenafly, New Jersey, on April 8, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Watson, Eve, 2014; cuid34847 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_15)
    Eve Watson was born in 1971 in Limerick, County Limerick, Ireland and was raised in Ballyagran, County Limerick. She graduated from Brown University in Providence, Rhode Island in 1996 and received her Ph.D. in psychology from University College Dublin in 2008. At the time of the 2014 interview, Watson was the Head of the Arts and Psychology Department at Independent College Dublin.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll at Eve Watson's office at Independent College in Dublin, Ireland on July 7, 2014. The interview covers Watson's family, early life, education, and working life. Watson discusses her family and early life in Ireland. She discusses the importance of athletics in her early life, her aptitude and interest in running, and the way in which this led to her attending Brown University in Providence, Rhode Island. She discusses her mental health before and during college, and her decision to her return to Ireland and enter therapy. She recounts her experiences in Kathmandu, Nepal between 1998 and 2001 and her decision to leave due to mental health issues. She recounts her decision to return to Ireland in late 2001 in order to pursue a degree in psychology and her work in the psychology department at Independent College Dublin.
  - Weadock, Joe, undated; cuid34747 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - White, Richard, undated; cuid34748 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Richard White (b. Flushing, New York, 1947), the Margaret Byrne Professor of American History at Stanford University, is the past President of the Organization of American Historians and a Pulitzer Prize-nominated author of several books regarding the American West, Native American history and Environmental history. Remembering Ahanagran: A History of Stories is his account of his mother's emigration from County Kerry.
  - Winch, Terry, undated; cuid34749 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Terry Winch (b. Bronx, New York, 1960) is a musician and writer. He is the author of five books of poems and two short story collections and has won the Columbia Book Award for The Great Indoors (1995) and the American Book Award for Irish Musicians/American Friends (2007). His experiences of growing up in a Bronx immigrant neighborhood are frequently his subjects. In 1977 he co-founded the traditional Irish music group Celtic Thunder.
- Z
  - Zurell, Eileen, Nov 6, 2008; cuid34750 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Eileen Houlihan Zurrell was born in New York in 1942 and grew up in Woodside, Queens. The daughter of 1920s immigrants from Co. Limerick, Ireland, her father was a member of Limerick Men's Association in New York. She held a career in administration. Eileen married her husband John in 1970 and began studying the Irish language after giving birth to her son and daughter in the early 1970s.
    Some of the key themes discussed in this interview include: different generations of Irish; 9/11 and loss of life in her parish; the 2008 election of Obama and comparisons with JFK; and her mother preparing the American parcel.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PCM660. The interview is approximately 90 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place in New York City on November 6, 2008, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.